{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "For how many days did Mahatma Gandhi's volunteers of the Salt satyagraha walk?",
            "optionA": "  24 ",
            "optionB": "  36 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi walked 24 days (12th March - 5th April, 1936) with 78 volunteers in salt Satygraha from Sabarmati to Dandi. ",
            "keyString": "248657s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements about Mahatma Gandhi's views on Satyagraha is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  It denotes assertion of the power of the human soul against social, political and economic dominance ",
            "optionB": "  It is the exercise of the purest soul force against all injustice, oppression and exploitation ",
            "optionC": "  It is the best weapon of the weak against the strong ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi's theory of Satayagraha was based on the acceptance of the concept of self-suffering ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the best weapon of the weak against the strong is the statement about Mahatma Gandhi's views on Satyagraha is not correct. ",
            "keyString": "248698s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not correct with reference to the Indian Freedom Struggle?",
            "optionA": "  The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave popular indignation and led to the JalianwallaBagh Massacre ",
            "optionB": "  Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association ",
            "optionD": "  In 1931, the Congress Session at Karachi opposed Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gandhi Irwin Pact was endorsed by the Congress in the Karachi Session of 1931, that was held from March 26-31. Gandhi was nominated to represent Congress in the Second Round Table Conference. So, there was anger in the public whose point was that why Gandhi did accept to sign the pact. ",
            "keyString": "248713s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader was not moderate?",
            "optionA": "  Dada Bhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Anand Charlu ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Madan Mohan Malviya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBipin Chandra Pal (7 November 1858 \u2013 20 May 1932) was an Indian nationalist, a freedom fighter, writer, orator and social reformer of Sylheti origin. He was one of the main architects of the Swadeshi movement. He stood against the partition of West Bengal. He was not moderate. ",
            "keyString": "248726s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the main part of Aurobindo's programme to achieve independence?",
            "optionA": "  Organisation of secret societies ",
            "optionB": "  Passive resistance ",
            "optionC": "  Constitutional agitation ",
            "optionD": "  Terrorism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Aurobindo Ghosh (1872-1950) who used the theory of Passive Resistance as a technique for social change during the period of India's national liberation movement. ",
            "keyString": "248738s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the leader of the Bardoli Satyagraha?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Vallabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Acharya J. ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bardoli Satyagraha of 1928, in the state of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a major episode of civil disobedience and revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. The movement was eventually led by Vallabhbhai Patel, and its success gave rise to Patel becoming one of the main leaders of the independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "343391s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Indian Independence Act of 1947, which of the following did not form a part of Pakistan?",
            "optionA": "  East Bengal and the West Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Sind and British Baluchistan ",
            "optionC": "  The North West Frontier ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Indian Independence Act of 1947, Assam did not form a part of Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "343438s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous 'Ratings Mutiny' (Revolt of a section of Indian soldiers serving in the Royal Indian Navy) in Bombay in February 1946 was calmed down largely by the efforts of",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  C Rajagopalachari ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe mutiny was ended by intervention of Sardar Patel, who after a meeting with M. S. Khan made a statement of ending the strike. The similar statement was made by Jinnah in Calcutta. The mutineers surrendered but despite the assurances of Congress and Muslim League, many mutineers were arrested, subjected to court martial and dismissed from the services. ",
            "keyString": "343462s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had given the slogan of 'Do or Die' during All India Congress Committee in Bombay and ratified the 'Quit India' resolution?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe historic session of the All India Congress Committee began on the 7th August and concluded after midnight of 8th August 1942 at Gowalia Tank Maidan, Bombay. In a speech entitled, \u201cDo or Die (Karo ya Mro),\u201d given on by Mahatma Gandhi urged the masses to act as an independent nation and not to follow the orders of the British. ",
            "keyString": "343482s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Working Committee of the Congress passed the Quit India resolution on",
            "optionA": "  July 14, 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  August 10, 1942 ",
            "optionC": "  August 8, 1942 ",
            "optionD": "  June 30, 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn July 1942, the Congress Working Committee met at Wardha. Here a long resolution was passed that demanded that the \u201cBritish Rule in India must end immediately\u201d. This resolution was an outcome of the change in attitude of Congress and Gandhi himself towards British. ",
            "keyString": "343500s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following tribes is associated with the \"Tana Bhagat\" movement?",
            "optionA": "  Uraon ",
            "optionB": "  Munda ",
            "optionC": "  Santhal ",
            "optionD": "  Konadora ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTana Bhagat movement was associated with Oraon. It is a tribal community in India (J.K.) He opposed British government (1914) for the unfair taxes imposed on them. They were the followers of Mahatma Gandhi and believes in Ahinsa(Non-Violence). ",
            "keyString": "435020s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. The Amritsar Session of the INC gave a great fillip to the Khilafat agitation.\nII. Khilafat conference held in Calcutta under Presidentship of Jinnah.\nIII. Khilafat Movement was started to support Ottoman Empire.\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct regarding Khilafat Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStatement (s) that are correct regarding Khilafat Movement are The Amritsar Session of the INC gave a great fillip to the Khilafat agitation and Khilafat Movement was started to support Ottoman Empire. ",
            "keyString": "435272s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Wahabi Movement named after its founder Abdul Wahab originated in . . . . . . in the 18th century with a view to restoring Islam to its pristine purity and order",
            "optionA": "  Manipal ",
            "optionB": "  Arabia ",
            "optionC": "  America ",
            "optionD": "  Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Wahabi Movement named after its founder Abdul Wahab originated in Arabia in the 18th century with a view to restoring Islam to its pristine purity and order. ",
            "keyString": "435476s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who led the Salt Satyagraha Movement with Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Mridula Sarabhai ",
            "optionC": "  Muthu Lakshmi ",
            "optionD": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarojini Naidu also led the Salt Satyagraha Movement with Gandhi. Sarojini Naidu was an Indian poet and political activist. While studying in London, she joined in on suffragist movements, and in 1924, she traveled through East Africa and South Africa promoting the nonviolent movements to obtain rights for Indians. ",
            "keyString": "435658s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Quit India Movement was Launched in 1942 in the month of",
            "optionA": "  January ",
            "optionB": "  March ",
            "optionC": "  August ",
            "optionD": "  December ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quit India Movement, or the 'August Movement', was a movement launched at the Bombay session of the All-India Congress Committee by Mahatma Gandhi on 8 August 1942, during World War II, demanding an end to British Rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "435833s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champaran and Kheda Satyagrahas were led by",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Satyagraha movements inspired by Mohandas Gandhi occurred in Champaran district of Bihar and the Kheda district of Gujarat on 1917 to 1918. Champaran Satyagraha was the first to be started, but the word Satyagraha was used for the first time in Anti Rowlatt Act agitation. ",
            "keyString": "515630s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the another name of 'Pledge of Indian Independence'?",
            "optionA": "  Declaration of Independence ",
            "optionB": "  Declaration of Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Declaration of Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhile the Poorna Swaraj Resolution was drafted by Jawaharlal Lal Nehru, the \u201cDeclaration of Independence\u201d pledge was drafted by Mahatma Gandhi in 1930 and it echoed the essence of American Declaration of Independence. After this pledge January 26, 1930 was declared as Independence Day by Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "515811s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had become the first Governor-General of India after independence?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Pethick Lawrence ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Mountbatten ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLouis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma remained Governor-General of India for some time after independence, but the two nations were otherwise headed by native Governors-General. ",
            "keyString": "515971s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not match correctly?",
            "optionA": "  Harappa : Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  Lothal : India ",
            "optionC": "  Dholavira : Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Banwali : Haryana ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDholavira is an archaeological site at Khadirbet in Bhachau Taluka of Kutch District, in the state of Gujarat in western India, which has taken its name from a modern-day village 1 kilometre south of it. ",
            "keyString": "516128s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the prime objective of M.K Gandhi's Salt Satyagraha?",
            "optionA": "  Complete Independence for India ",
            "optionB": "  Economic relief to the common people ",
            "optionC": "  Repeal of salt laws ",
            "optionD": "  Curtailment of the Government's powers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Gandhi broke the salt laws at 6:30 am on 6 April 1930, it sparked large scale acts of civil disobedience against the British Raj salt laws by millions of Indians. The Salt Satyagraha campaign was based upon Gandhi's principles of non-violent protest called satyagraha, which he loosely translated as \"truth-force\". ",
            "keyString": "516282s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The background of the foundation of the Muslim League at . . . . . . on 30 December 1906 may be traced back to the establishment of the Indian national congress in 1885",
            "optionA": "  Dhaka ",
            "optionB": "  Shahbag ",
            "optionC": "  Simla ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe background of the foundation of the Muslim League at Dhaka on 30 December 1906 may be traced back to the establishment of the indian national congress in 1885. ",
            "keyString": "598507s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year did the Indian National Congress hold its first meeting in Bombay?",
            "optionA": "  1832 ",
            "optionB": "  1844 ",
            "optionC": "  1885 ",
            "optionD": "  1890 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first meeting was scheduled to be held in Poona, but due to a cholera outbreak it was shifted to Bombay. Womesh Chandra Bonnerjee was the first president of the Congress; the first session was held from 28\u201331 December 1885, and was attended by 72 delegates. ",
            "keyString": "598692s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Civil Disobedience Movement was suspended after the Gandhi-Irwin Pact. Why did the Congress decide to resume the movement In January 1932?",
            "optionA": "  Failure of the Second Round Table Conference ",
            "optionB": "  Repudiation of the Gandhi-Irwin Pact by the British Government ",
            "optionC": "  British policies of repression ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Congress decide to resume the movement In January 1932 because Of Failure of the Second Round Table Conference, Repudiation of the Gandhi-Irwin Pact by the British Government and British policies of repression. ",
            "keyString": "653155s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Khilafat Movement of the Indian Muslims related to",
            "optionA": "  provision of separate electorate for the Muslims in the Act of 1919 ",
            "optionB": "  restoration of territories to Turkey captured by Britain in the First World War ",
            "optionC": "  restoration of the Sultan of Turkey who was Caliph of the Muslim World ",
            "optionD": "  lifting of martial law in Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Khilafat movement was an agitation by Indian Muslims, allied with Indian nationalists, to pressure the British government to preserve the authority of the Ottoman Sultan as Caliph of Islam after World War I. ",
            "keyString": "653406s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following brought Aurobindo Ghose into the fold of the Indian National Movement?",
            "optionA": "  The famines of 1896-97 and 1899-1900 ",
            "optionB": "  The partition of Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  The Surat Split ",
            "optionD": "  The Jallianwala Bagh episode ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn July 1905 then Viceroy of India, Lord Curzon, partitioned Bengal. This sparked an outburst of public anger against the British, leading to civil unrest and a nationalist campaign by groups of revolutionaries, who included Aurobindo. ",
            "keyString": "653579s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader given the term 'insenate waste' on the burning of the foreign clothes during the Non-Cooperation Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Reading ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Rabindra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Mohammad Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRabindra Nath Tagore gave the term 'insenate waste' on the burning of the foreign clothes during the Non-Cooperation Movement. ",
            "keyString": "653766s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event was the reason for suspension of the Non-Cooperation Movement?",
            "optionA": "  The non Co-operators were not enthusiastic ",
            "optionB": "  The leaders like Subhas Chandra Bose were against it ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhiji bowed to the pressure of the British government ",
            "optionD": "  Chauri Chaura incident ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi feared that the movement might lead to popular violence. The non-cooperation movement was launched on 1 August 1920 and withdrawn in February 1922 after the Chauri Chaura incident. ",
            "keyString": "654213s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader who presided All India Congress Committee session on 9th August?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Aruna Asif Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Annie Besant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe government responded by arresting the major leaders and all members of the Congress Working Committee and thus tried to pre-empt the movement from success. Young Aruna Asaf Ali presided over the remainder of the session on 9 August and hoisted the Congress flag at the Gowalia Tank Maidan. ",
            "keyString": "712367s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name three important forms of Satyagraha",
            "optionA": "  Non-cooperation, civil disobedience and boycott ",
            "optionB": "  Boycott, civil disobedience and rebellion ",
            "optionC": "  Non-cooperation, revolution and referendum ",
            "optionD": "  Revolution, plebiscite and boycott ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji's overall method of non-violence is called 'Satyagrah'. Three forms of Satyagraha are: Non-Cooperation, Civil disobedience and boycott. ",
            "keyString": "712553s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following provision was not included in the Nehru Report?",
            "optionA": "  India must be given Dominion status ",
            "optionB": "  The Governor General must be only the constitutional head ",
            "optionC": "  There was to be no separate electorate ",
            "optionD": "  Diarchy should be introduced both at the centre as well as provinces ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDyarchy should be introduced both at the centre as well as provinces was not included in the Nehru Report. ",
            "keyString": "712730s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Quit India Resolution was passed on",
            "optionA": "  August 8, 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  August 28, 1942 ",
            "optionC": "  April 4, 1928 ",
            "optionD": "  April 24, 1928 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quit India Movement, or the 'August Movement', was a movement launched at the Bombay session of the All-India Congress Committee by Mahatma Gandhi on 8 August 1942, during World War II, demanding an end to British Rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "712911s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Independence Act was passed in",
            "optionA": "  18 July 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  01 August 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  01 June 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  01 September 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Independence Act, which was based on the Mountbatten plan of June 3, was passed by the British parliament on July 5, 1947 and received royal assent or approval on July 18, 1947. ",
            "keyString": "713069s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sir Syed Ahmed Khan had started a reform movement among the Muslim, called the __________ Movement",
            "optionA": "  Sufi ",
            "optionB": "  Aligarh ",
            "optionC": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionD": "  Wahabi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Aligarh Movement was the push to establish a modern system of education for the Muslim population of British India, during the later decades of the 19th century. The movement\u2032s name derives from the fact that its core and origins lay in the city of Aligarh in Northern India and, in particular, with the foundation of the Mohammedan Anglo Oriental Collegiate School in 1875. The founder of the oriental college, and the other educational institutions that developed from it, was Sir Syed Ahmed Khan. He became the leading light of the wider Aligarh Movement. ",
            "keyString": "770480s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Namdhari, or Kuka, movement had its origin in the __________ corner of the Sikh kingdom, away from the places of royal pomp and grandeur",
            "optionA": "  North-west ",
            "optionB": "  North-south ",
            "optionC": "  North-east ",
            "optionD": "  South ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdhari, or Kuka, movement also had its origin in the north-west corner of the Sikh kingdom, away from the places of royal pomp and grandeur. It harked back to a way of life more in keeping with the spiritual tradition of the community. Its principal object was to spread the true spirit of Sikhism shorn of tawdry customs and mannerism, which had been growing on it since the beginning of Sikh monarchy. ",
            "keyString": "770671s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was the achieved milestone of the Non-Cooperation Movement of 1921?",
            "optionA": "  It stopped the injustice done to the Khilafat ",
            "optionB": "  Indian obtains some political rights ",
            "optionC": "  The Hindus and the Muslims came closer in political pursuit ",
            "optionD": "  It avenged the Punjab atrocities ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian obtains some political rights was the achieved milestone of the Non-Cooperation Movement of 1921. ",
            "keyString": "770848s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ was the Founder Father of Aligarh movement",
            "optionA": "  Sir Syed Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Maqsud Ali ",
            "optionC": "  Abul kalam Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Karim Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAligarh Muslim University is the creation of the movement. In 1886 Sir Syed Ahmad Khan founded the All India Muhammadan Educational Conference in order to promote more broadly the educational objectives of Aligarh Movement. ",
            "keyString": "771004s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan's Red Shirt Movement were known as",
            "optionA": "  Khidmatgars (Servants) ",
            "optionB": "  Insan-i-Khidmatgar (Servants of the people) ",
            "optionC": "  Khuda-i-Khidamatgar (Servants of God) ",
            "optionD": "  Angels of Freedom ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan's Red Shirt Movement were known as Khuda-i-Khidamatgar (Servants of God). ",
            "keyString": "771160s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The father of extremist movement in India is",
            "optionA": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gopal Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Bal Gangadhar Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLokmanya Tilak was one of the prominent Indian independence activists. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. He was the father of Extremist Movement. The British Colonial authorities derogatorily called him 'Father of the Indian Unrest' ",
            "keyString": "835135s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two socio-religious reform movements founded in India in 1875 were",
            "optionA": "  Brahmo Samaj and Prarthana Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Arya Samaj and Ramakrishna Mission ",
            "optionC": "  Theosophical Society and Arya Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Aligarh Movement and Servants of Indian Society ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arya Samaj is a monotheistic Hindu reform movement founded in India by Swami Dayananda in 1875 at Bombay. He was a sannyasin (ascetic) who believed in the infallible authority of the Vedas. The Theosophical Society was founded in the United States by Madam H.P Blavatsky and Colonel H.S. Olcott, who later came to India and founded the headquarters of the Society at Adyar near Madras in 1886. ",
            "keyString": "836211s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which movement got the support from both Hindus and Muslims?",
            "optionA": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Quit India Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Champaran Stayagraha ",
            "optionD": "  Anti-Partition Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon-Cooperation Movement got the support from both Hindus and Muslims. Muslims were opposing British government because of division of Turkey by the allied powers during frist world war. ",
            "keyString": "836713s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Apart from the Quit India Movement which started on 9th August 1942,  what other sensational activity of the freedom fighters was done on 9th August?",
            "optionA": "  Salt Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Boycott of Simon Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Champaran Satyagraha ",
            "optionD": "  Kakori Mail train robbery ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 9th August 1925, Kakori Mail train robbery took place at the town of Kakori about 10 miles north west of Lucknow. The raiders were members of Hindustan Republican Association. ",
            "keyString": "836966s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Quit India Movement,'Parallel Government' was constituted at",
            "optionA": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionD": "  Ballia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Quit India Movement (1942) parallel Government established in a part of India i.e in Ballia (By Chittu Pandey), Tamluk(Bengal), Satara(Maharastra). The parallel government of Satara ran for long time comparatively to others. ",
            "keyString": "837358s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The roots of the 1857 revolt lay in",
            "optionA": "  Blatantly discriminatory policies ",
            "optionB": "  Exploitative land revenue policy ",
            "optionC": "  The policy of greased cartridges ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe British ruled over India for about two centuries. They started interference in the religious matters and other social practices of Hindus and Muslims and it infuriated the Indians and their anger resulted in the armed revolt of 1857. The roots of the 1857 revolt lay in Blatantly discriminatory policies, exploitative land revenue policy and the policy of greased cartridges. ",
            "keyString": "895545s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Revolt of 1857 was started by",
            "optionA": "  The sepoys ",
            "optionB": "  The zamindars ",
            "optionC": "  The peasants ",
            "optionD": "  The plantations workers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Mutiny, also called Sepoy Mutiny, widespread but unsuccessful rebellion against British rule in India in 1857\u201358. Begun in Meerut by Indian troops (sepoys) in the service of the British East India Company, it spread to Delhi, Agra, Kanpur, and Lucknow. ",
            "keyString": "895581s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The revolt of 1857 had its beginning in",
            "optionA": "  Meerut ",
            "optionB": "  Plassey ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Rebellion of 1857 is also called the Indian Mutiny, the Sepoy Mutiny, North India's First War of Independence or North India's first struggle for independence. It began on 10 May 1857 at Meerut, as a mutiny of sepoys of the British East India Company's army. ",
            "keyString": "895599s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An effect of the 1857 revolt was that",
            "optionA": "  The spirit of rebellion in Indian was crushed ",
            "optionB": "  The British became totally demoralized ",
            "optionC": "  The British abandoned their repressive policies ",
            "optionD": "  Unity was forged between the Hindus and Muslims ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important impact of revolt of 1857 is that the administration of India was transferred from the East India Company to the British Crown. The queen's proclamation of 1858 announced that the policy of territorial extension was to be abandoned. Unity was forged between the Hindus and Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "895615s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Revolt of 1857 failed mainly because",
            "optionA": "  of superior resources of the British empire ",
            "optionB": "  it was poorly organised and the rebels had no common ideal ",
            "optionC": "  it had very little nationalist sentiment ",
            "optionD": "  it was localised, restricted and scattered ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Revolt of 1857 was localized and poorly organized. Due to lack of communication facilities, the sepoys of the widely dispersed cantonments could not act simultaneously in a concerted manner. The sepoys lacked common ideal before them. The sepoys at Delhi decided to recovery the glory of the Mughal. At Gwalior and Kanpur, Nana Sahib was proclaimed a Peshwa. Rani Lakhmi Bai fought for her Jhansi. The orthodox section among the Hindus and the Muslims were concerned with their religions. There was no unity among the Hindus and the Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "895631s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champaran Satyagraha was in __________",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Champaran Satyagraha of 1917 was the first Satyagraha movement inspired by Gandhi and a major revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. It was a farmer's uprising that took place in Champaran district of Bihar, India during the British colonial period. The farmers were protesting against to grow opium with barely any payment for it. ",
            "keyString": "973515s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following initiated the Kheda Satyagraha?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Mohanlal Pandya ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohanlal Pandya was an Indian freedom fighter, social reformer and one of the earliest followers of Mahatma Gandhi. Mohanlal Pandya was nicknamed as \"Onion Thief\" (\"Dungli Chor\") by Gandhi because he had harvested onion from the land which was taken away by the British Government. He initiated the Kheda Satyagraha. ",
            "keyString": "973719s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following committee and act is associated with the Sedition act?",
            "optionA": "  Rowlatt Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Muddiman Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Butler Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRowlatt Acts, (February 1919), legislation passed by the Imperial Legislative Council, the legislature of British India. The acts allowed certain political cases to be tried without juries and permitted internment of suspects without trial. They were based on the report of Justice S.A.T. Rowlatt's committee of 1918. ",
            "keyString": "973899s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Given below are the names of prominent leaders and their respective operational areas during the the revolt period. Select the incorrect pair",
            "optionA": "  Rani Laxmibai   -   Indore ",
            "optionB": "  Khan Bahadur Khan   -   RuhelKhand ",
            "optionC": "  Kunwar Singh     -    Sahabad ",
            "optionD": "  Nana Saheb      -    Kanpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRani Laxmibai- Jhansi",
            "keyString": "974070s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ahmedabad Satyagraha of Gandhi was directed against",
            "optionA": "  British mill owners and government officials ",
            "optionB": "  Indian mill owners and non government officials ",
            "optionC": "  British non-government officials ",
            "optionD": "  Indian government officials ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Ahmedabad Satyagraha of Gandhi was directed against Indian mill owners and non-government officials. ",
            "keyString": "974236s37m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Gandhi call the Congress Working Committee to announce the suspension of Non-Cooperation movement?",
            "optionA": "  Bardoli ",
            "optionB": "  Poona ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-Cooperation Movement was withdrawn after the Chauri Chaura incident in February 1922. The Working Committee of the Congress met at Bardoli on 11 and 12 February 1922 and passed a resolution suspending mass civil disobedience till the atmosphere was perfectly non-violent. ",
            "keyString": "53440s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main objectives of the Non-Cooperation Movement were",
            "optionA": "  restoration of the old status of the Caliph (Khilafat Demand) and attainment of Swaraj for India ",
            "optionB": "  protest against the Punjab wrongs and withdrawal of the Rowlatt Acts ",
            "optionC": "  lifting of martial law from Punjab and withdrawal of repressive laws ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main objectives of the Non-Cooperation Movement were restoration of the old status of the Caliph (Khilafat Demand) and attainment of Swaraj for India. ",
            "keyString": "53754s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1918, Mahatma Gandhi went to__________ to organise a satyagraha movement amongst\ncotton mill workers",
            "optionA": "  Madras ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Surat ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kheda Satyagraha of 1918, in the Kheda district of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a Satyagraha movement organized by Mohandas Gandhi. It was a major revolt in the Indian independence movement. It was the third Satyagraha movement after Champaran Satyagraha and Ahmedabad mill strike. ",
            "keyString": "53969s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following movement did Mahatma Gandhi make the first use of Hunger Strike as a weapon?",
            "optionA": "  Non-Cooperation Movement, 1920-22 ",
            "optionB": "  Rowlatt Satyagraha, 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmedabad Strike, 1918 ",
            "optionD": "  Bardoli Satyagraha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAhmedabad Mill Strike, 1918 was one of the initial movements led by Gandhi in the beginning of 20th century after his return from South Africa. It was one of the formative events in the political career of Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "54158s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Home Rule Movement was aimed at",
            "optionA": "  complete independence for India ",
            "optionB": "  complete autonomy to India ",
            "optionC": "  self-government for India within the British Commonwealth ",
            "optionD": "  larger participation of Indians in India's administration ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant gave new hope to the country. \u201cThe moment of England's difficulty is the moment of India's opportunity.\u201d She started the Home Rule League Movement to be later supported fully by Tilak. It aimed at self-government for India within the British Commonwealth. ",
            "keyString": "54335s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress had adopted the famous Poorna Swaraj (Complete Independence) resolution at its session held at",
            "optionA": "  Karachi ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National Congress, at its historic Lahore session in December 1929, under the presidency of Jawaharlal Nehru, adopted a resolution to gain complete independence from the British. ",
            "keyString": "154102s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader was not associated with extremist leadership of Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "optionB": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA. O. Hume was not associated with extremist leadership of Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "154309s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Bal Gangadhar Tilak?",
            "optionA": "  He wrote 'Gita Rahasya' ",
            "optionB": "  He started Ganpati Festval in 1893 ",
            "optionC": "  He launched a newspaper 'Kesari' in English ",
            "optionD": "  He started home rule league in 1916 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMore than education, it was journalism that became Tilak's way to reach out to people. In 1881 he launched two newspapers\u2014the Kesari ( Lion) in Marathi and the Mahratta in English. ",
            "keyString": "241319s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satyagraha Sabha was formed by Gandhi at",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Poona ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi did not believe that the existing institutions could handle such a noble weapon. So a separate institution named Satyagraha Sabha was formed, its headquarters were in Bombay. ",
            "keyString": "241505s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Satyagraha finds expression in",
            "optionA": "  Sudden outbursts of violence ",
            "optionB": "  Armed conflicts ",
            "optionC": "  Non-Cooperation ",
            "optionD": "  Communal riots ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatyagraha expressed in Non-cooperation, Non-Violence was the basic features of this Satyagraha. For Gandhi, satyagraha went far beyond mere \"passive resistance\" and became strength in practising non-violent methods. In his words: Truth (satya) implies love, and firmness (agraha) engenders and therefore serves as a synonym for force. ",
            "keyString": "241666s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who founded the organization \"servants of Indian society\"?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. ",
            "optionB": " R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopal Krishan Gokhale founded the \"Servants of Indian Society\" in Pune Maharastra. ",
            "keyString": "241823s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that the congress is tottering to its fall, and one of my great ambitions, while in India, is to assist it to a peaceful demise?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Curzon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Dufferin ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon believed \u201cthat the Congress is tottering to its fall, and one of my greatest ambitions while in India is to assist it to a peaceful demise.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "241978s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was congress split?",
            "optionA": "  At Surat session in 1907 ",
            "optionB": "  At Benares session in 1905 ",
            "optionC": "  At Madras in1908 ",
            "optionD": "  At Lahore in1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National Congress(INC) which was established in 1885 was divided into two groups(in the year 1907) mainly by extremists and moderates at the Surat Session of the Congress.The period 1885-1905 was known as the period of the moderates as moderates dominated the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "347929s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Mahatma Gandhi first apply his technique of Satyagraha?",
            "optionA": "  Dandi ",
            "optionB": "  Noakhali ",
            "optionC": "  England ",
            "optionD": "  South Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi first conceived satyagraha in 1906 in response to a law discriminating against Asians that was passed by the British colonial government of the Transvaal in South Africa. In 1917 the first satyagraha campaign in India was mounted in the indigo-growing district of Champaran. ",
            "keyString": "348154s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the Muslim League?",
            "optionA": "  It was established by the Nawab Salimullah ",
            "optionB": "  It was established in Calcutta in 1906 ",
            "optionC": "  The league supported the partition on Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  The league opposed the Swadeshi movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFounded in In 30 December 1906, the All-India Muslim League was founded at Dhaka. Founders: Khwaja Salimullah, Vikar-ul-Mulk, Syed Amir Ali, Syed Nabiullah. The All-India Muslim League (popularised as Muslim League) was a political party established during the early years of the 20th century in the British Indian Empire. Its strong advocacy for the establishment of a separate Muslim-majority nation-state, Pakistan, successfully led to the partition of British India in 1947 by the British Empire. ",
            "keyString": "431049s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champaran Satyagraha was led by __________",
            "optionA": "  Amaresh Chakravarty ",
            "optionB": "  Pulinbehari Sarkar ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Champaran Satyagraha of 1917 was the first Satyagraha movement inspired by Gandhi and a major revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. It was a farmer's uprising that took place in Champaran district of Bihar, India during the British colonial period. The farmers were protesting against to grow opium with barely any payment for it. ",
            "keyString": "431086s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Home Rule Society, popularly called 'India House' , had been established in London to promote the cause of Indian independence, by",
            "optionA": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionB": "  Madan Lal Dhingra ",
            "optionC": "  Shyamji Krishna Varma ",
            "optionD": "  V D Savarkar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe society was foundations of the India House and, along with Krishna Varma's journal The Indian Sociologist, was the foundation of the militant Indian nationalist movement in Britain. ",
            "keyString": "431105s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the Bardoli Satyagraha, the title of 'Sardar' to Vallabhbhai Patel was given by",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Maulana Abdul Kalam Azad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVallabhbhai Patel was respectfully called Sardar by his colleagues and followers during the satyagraha against steep tax hikes in a famine hit Bardoli in 1928. He had led the Satyagraha when Gandhiji was imprisoned, at the request of the congress members. Sardar Patel was freed in 1931, following the Gandhi-Irwin Pact. ",
            "keyString": "431122s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct regarding Poona Pact (1932)?\nI. It refers to an agreement between Babasaheb Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi signed on 24 September 1932 at Yerwada Central Jail in Pune (now in Maharashtra), India.\nII. It was signed by Pt Madan Mohan Malviya and B. R. Ambedkar and some Dalit leaders to break the fast unto death undertaken by Gandhi in Yerwada prison to annul the Macdonald Award giving separate electorates to Dalits for electing members of state legislative assemblies in British India",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statement(s) that are correct regarding Poona Pact (1932) are It refers to an agreement between Babasaheb Ambedkar and Mahatma Gandhi signed on 24 September 1932 at Yerwada Central Jail in Pune (now in Maharashtra), India and It was signed by Pt Madan Mohan Malviya and B.R. Ambedkar and some Dalit leaders to break the fast unto death undertaken by Gandhi in Yerwada prison to annul the Macdonald Award giving separate electorates to Dalits for electing members of state legislative assemblies in British India. ",
            "keyString": "434295s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Do or Die' (Karenge ya Marenge) Gandhiji gave this Mantra to the nation on the eve of which mass movement?",
            "optionA": "  Rowlatt Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Salt Satyagraha ",
            "optionC": "  Quit India Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuit India Movement was started on 8 Aug,1942 in Bombay under the leadership of Mahatma Gandhi. In this movement he gave a slogan \"Do or Die\". Mahatama Gandhi gave this slogan first time during this movement. ",
            "keyString": "487724s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In violation of the Salt Laws, Gandhiji started a movement called",
            "optionA": "  Non-Cooperation movement ",
            "optionB": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Disobedience movement ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo violate salt law Gandhiji decided to march fromSabarmati to Dandi (12 March,1930 - 5 April,1930) with 78 delegates. This march is known as Dandi March. This was the beginning of civil disobedience in India and it spread over the different parts of country. ",
            "keyString": "487944s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the points stressed by Mahatma Gandhi while exhorting the people to join the Quit India Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Forget the differences between the Hindus and Muslims and think of yourselves as Indians only. ",
            "optionB": "  our quarrel is not with British people, we fight their imperialism and we must purge ourselves of hatred. ",
            "optionC": "  Feel from today that you are a free man and pot a dependent. Do or die. Either free India or die in the the attempt. ",
            "optionD": "  Freedom of India is an end that will purify all means employed to achieve it. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFreedom of India is an end that will purify all means employed to achieve it was not one of the points stressed by Mahatma Gandhi while exhorting the people to join the Quit India Movement. ",
            "keyString": "488131s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year did Gandhiji start Satyagraha Movement?",
            "optionA": "  1919 ",
            "optionB": "  1917 ",
            "optionC": "  1934 ",
            "optionD": "  1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhiji started first Satyagraha movement in 1909 in South Africa and in India started in 1917 from Champaran. ",
            "keyString": "488304s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Non-Cooperation movement had been launched by Gandhi in the year",
            "optionA": "  1916 ",
            "optionB": "  1919 ",
            "optionC": "  1920 ",
            "optionD": "  1923 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-Cooperation Movement was a significant but short phase of the Indian independence movement from British rule. It was led by Mahatma Gandhi after the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre and lasted from 1920 to February 1922. It aimed to resist British rule in India through non-violent means, or \"Ahimsa\". ",
            "keyString": "488472s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A resolution declaring Purna Swaraj (complete Independence) as Indian's political goal was passed in the __________ Congress of 1929",
            "optionA": "  Shimla ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National Congress now changed its stance: it gave up demands for dominion status and instead, at its Lahore Session in 1929, passed the 'Purna Swaraj' resolution that called for complete independence. The resolution marked the beginning of a large-scale political movement against colonial rule. ",
            "keyString": "532784s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who started the English weekly 'New India'?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionB": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Dada Bhai Naoroji ",
            "optionD": "  Madan Mohan Malviya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBipin Chandra Pal started New India(Weekly) and Annie Besant started New India(Daily) started to spread patriotic feelings in the people of India. ",
            "keyString": "533000s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Gandhiji form the Satyagraha Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Poona ",
            "optionD": "  Nagpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi did not believe that the existing institutions could handle such a noble weapon. So a separate institution named Satyagraha Sabha was formed, its headquarters were in Bombay. ",
            "keyString": "533169s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The India Independence Bill was first presented in the House of Commons in London on",
            "optionA": "  August 10,1947 ",
            "optionB": "  August 1,1947 ",
            "optionC": "  July 14,1947 ",
            "optionD": "  July 4,1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Independence Act, which was based on the Mountbatten plan of June 3, was passed by the British parliament on July 5, 1947 and received royal assent or approval on July 18, 1947. ",
            "keyString": "533327s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kheda Satyagraha is related to __________",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Thana ",
            "optionD": "  Malabar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kheda Satyagraha of 1918, in the Kheda district of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a Satyagraha movement organized by Mohandas Gandhi. It was a major revolt in the Indian independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "533531s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not true about the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  It was formed in 1885 ",
            "optionB": "  W.",
            "optionC": " Bannerjee was the first president of congress ",
            "optionD": "  It was formed when 72 delegates from all the presidencies and provinces of India met at Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAllan Octavian Hume, CB ICS (4 June 1829 \u2013 31 July 1912) was a member of the Imperial Civil Service (later the Indian Civil Service), a political reformer, ornithologist and botanist who worked in British India. He was one of the founders of the Indian National Congress, a political party that was later to lead in the Indian independence movement. A notable ornithologist, Hume has been called \"the Father of Indian Ornithology\" and, by those who found him dogmatic, \"the Pope of Indian ornithology\". ",
            "keyString": "603616s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leaders were associated with the Revolt of Khasis in 1820-32?",
            "optionA": "  Tirut Singh and Bar Manik ",
            "optionB": "  Sambu Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Sidhu and Kanu ",
            "optionD": "  Vir Manik ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis tribal movement was led by Tirut Singh and Bar Manik, who fought against British attempts to take over control of the Khasis Hills. In 1832, the war ended when British captured Tirut Singh, as one of chief betrayed him for some pieces of gold. He died on July 17,1835. His death anniversary is commemorated every year as a state holiday in Meghalaya. ",
            "keyString": "647849s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi in 1919 decided to launch a nation wide satyagraha against the proposed __________",
            "optionA": "  Simon Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Rowlatt Act ",
            "optionC": "  Salt Act ",
            "optionD": "  Pitt's India Act ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi decided to launch a nation wide Satyagraha against the Rowlatt Act (Black Law and Blind Law). ",
            "keyString": "648230s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champaran, the site of Gandhi's first experiment in Satyagraha, is located in the state of",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Champaran Satyagraha of 1917 was the first Satyagraha movement inspired by Gandhi and a major revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. It was a farmer's uprising that took place in Champaran district of Bihar, India during the British colonial period. ",
            "keyString": "648611s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Satyagraha was held at Nagpur in 1923?",
            "optionA": "  Salt Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Individual Satyagraha ",
            "optionC": "  Ryots Satyagraha ",
            "optionD": "  Flag Satyagraha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlag Satyagraha was held at Nagpur in 1923. It was the peaceful civil disobedience that focused on exercising the right and freedom to hoist the nationalist flag. ",
            "keyString": "648947s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who led the Bardoli Satyagraha in 1928?",
            "optionA": "  Morarji Desai ",
            "optionB": "  M. K. Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Mahadev Desai ",
            "optionD": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bardoli Satyagraha of 1928, in the state of Gujarat, India during the period of the British Raj, was a major episode of civil disobedience and revolt in the Indian Independence Movement. The movement was eventually led by Vallabhbhai Patel, and its success gave rise to Patel becoming one of the main leaders of the independence movement. ",
            "keyString": "649183s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khilafat Movement was organised to protest against the injustice done to",
            "optionA": "  Persia ",
            "optionB": "  Turkey ",
            "optionC": "  Arabia ",
            "optionD": "  Egypt ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Turkey, a national movement arose under Mustafa Kemal Ataturk, who was a Pro-western nationalist. He, supported by the western powers, abolished the position of the Caliph. Naturally the Muslims in India became anti British, as the power and influence of their religious leader was ended. Muslims were especially upset about the future of the Islamic places of worship after the allied powers had partitioned the Turkish Empire. ",
            "keyString": "694778s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the failure of the Civil Disobedience Movement, Mahatma Gandhi laid emphasis on",
            "optionA": "  compromise with the British ",
            "optionB": "  limited use of Violence ",
            "optionC": "  constructive programme ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe movement continued to linger in a non-effective manner till early April 1934 when Mahatma Gandhi announced his decision to withdraw the Civil Disobedience Movement. With these developments, the second phase of the Civil Disobedience Movement came to an end. Theconstructiveprogrammemayotherwiseandmorefittinglybecalled constructionofPoornaSwaraj or complete independence by truthful and nonviolent means. EffortforconstructionofIndependencesocalledthroughviolentand, therefore,necessarilyuntruthfulmeansweknowonlytoopainfully.Lookatthe dailydestructionofproperty,lifeandtruthinthepresentwar. CompleteIndependencethroughtruthandnon-violencemeansthe independenceofeveryunit,beitthehumblestofthenation,without distinctionofrace,colourorcreed. ",
            "keyString": "694976s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The peasant movements, revolts, riots, struggles, etc. in 19th century, India remained mainly localised because",
            "optionA": "  they were mainly directed against enhancement in rent, evictions, usurious practices of moneylenders, etc. ",
            "optionB": "  the peasants had no leadership and organisation ",
            "optionC": "  they grew out of local grievances ",
            "optionD": "  the big landlords were allies of the British ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe peasant movements, revolts, riots, struggles, etc. in 19th century, India remained mainly localised because they grew out of local grievances. ",
            "keyString": "695142s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi launched the Civil Disobedience Movement in 1930 from",
            "optionA": "  Sabarmati Ashram ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionC": "  Porbandar ",
            "optionD": "  Dandi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi launched civil disobedience movement on 12th March, 1930 (with break of salt law). Mahatma Gandhi launched the Civil Disobedience Movement in 1930 from Sabarmati Ashram. ",
            "keyString": "695301s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the 'Quit India Movement' launched by Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  1946 ",
            "optionB": "  1939 ",
            "optionC": "  1942 ",
            "optionD": "  1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1942 at the All-India Congress Committee session in Bombay, Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi launched the 'Quit India' movement. The next day, Gandhi, Nehru and many other leaders of the Indian National Congress were arrested by the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "695457s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did M.K Gandhi suspend non cooperation movement after the violent act of peasants at Police station of Chauri Chaura, near Gorakhpur in UP?",
            "optionA": "  Feb 1922 ",
            "optionB": "  Mar 1922 ",
            "optionC": "  Jan 1920 ",
            "optionD": "  Feb 1920 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFeb 1922 ",
            "keyString": "748435s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is called as \"beacon of light of Asia\"",
            "optionA": "  Gautam Buddha ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Subhash Chandra Bose ",
            "optionD": "  Abdul Gaffer khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNetaji Subhash Chandra Bose is known as beacon of light of Asia. ",
            "keyString": "748860s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per Indian Independence Act, the suzerainty of His Majesty over the Indian State would come to an end on __________",
            "optionA": "  15 August 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  14 August 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  15 August 1950 ",
            "optionD": "  26 January 1950 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per Indian Independence Act, the Suzerainty of His Majesty over the Indian State would come to an end on 14 August 1947. ",
            "keyString": "749159s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Moplah revolt took place?",
            "optionA": "  Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Moplah Rebellion or the Malabar Rebellion was an extended version of the Khilafat Movement in Kerala in 1921. The Government had declared the Congress and Khilafat meetings illegal. So, a reaction in Kerala began against the crackdown of the British in Eranad and Valluvanad taluks of Malabar. ",
            "keyString": "749490s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following Satyagraha campaigns, Mahatma Gandhi did not participate directly?",
            "optionA": "  Rajkot Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Kheda Satyagraha ",
            "optionD": "  Vaikom Satyagraha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Rajkot Satyagraha campaigns, Mahatma Gandhi did not participate directly. ",
            "keyString": "749773s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the Journal published in Britain by the Committee of the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta Gazette ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal Tribune ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta Tribune ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is the journal published in Britain by the committee of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "800420s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is regarded as the father and founder of the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  SN Banerjee ",
            "optionC": "  AO Hume ",
            "optionD": "  Pheroze Shah Mehta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe important role of Allan Octavian Hume (1829-1912) in the establishment and early development of the Indian National Congress is generally acknowledged. It was not, indeed, without good reason that many first generation leaders of the movement regarded Hume as the 'Father of Congress'. Hume has been called \"the Father of Indian Ornithology\" and, by those who found him dogmatic, \"the Pope of Indian ornithology\". ",
            "keyString": "800636s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not one of the historic decisions of the Lahore Session (1929) of the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Decision to launch a programme of civil disobedience ",
            "optionB": "  Complete independence (Poorna Swaraj) as the goal of the Indian National Congress ",
            "optionC": "  Decision to observe January 26 as the Poorna Swaraj Day ",
            "optionD": "  To treat the communal problem as a national issue ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo treat the communal problem as a national issue was not one of the historic decisions of the Lahore Session (1929) of the Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "800841s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which pact, warm relations were established between \"Garam dal\" and Naram dal\" the two groups of the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Gandhi-Irwin Pact ",
            "optionB": "  Lucknow Pact ",
            "optionC": "  Karachi agreement ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore declaration ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe bitter relations between two groups of Indian national Congress i.e. Garam Dal (Extremists) and Naram Dal(Moderates) were pacified or brought back to Normal in Lucknow pact 1916. The Chairman was Ambika Charan Majoomdar. ",
            "keyString": "801025s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Satyagraha of Gandhiji for the cause of indigo farmers was observed at",
            "optionA": "  Champaran ",
            "optionB": "  ChauriChaura ",
            "optionC": "  Bardoli ",
            "optionD": "  Sabarmati ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Satyagraha of Gandhiji in India was observed at Champaran in 1917. In Champran Tin-Kathiya system was implemented by the Britishers i.e, Compulsory farming of Indigo in 3/20 of the total land. ",
            "keyString": "853966s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Neel Darpan' a play depicting the revolt against the Indigo planters was written by",
            "optionA": "  Dinbandhu Mitra ",
            "optionB": "  Bankim Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionC": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionD": "  Naveen Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeel Darpan was a Bengali play written by Dinabandhu Mitra in 1858\u20131859. The play was essential to Nilbidraha, or Indigo revolt of February\u2013March 1859 in Bengal, when farmers refused to sow indigo in their fields as a protest against exploitative farming under the British Raj. ",
            "keyString": "854173s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The leader who quit politics, retired to Pondicherry and set up an ashram there, was",
            "optionA": "  Lokmanya TiIak ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  Bhikaji Cama ",
            "optionD": "  Sri Aurobindo Ghose ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Sri Aurobindo (born Aurobindo Ghose; 15 August 1872 \u2013 5 December 1950) was an Indian philosopher, yogi, guru, poet, and nationalist. He quit politics, retired to Pondicherry and set up an ashram there. ",
            "keyString": "854544s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From where did Acharya Vinoba Bhave start the Individual Satyagraha in 1940?",
            "optionA": "  Nadiad in Gujrat ",
            "optionB": "  Pavnar in Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Adyar in Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Guntur in Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAcharya Vinobha Bhave Start individual Satyagraha from Pavnar in Maharashtra in 1940. He was the first individual Satyagrahi and Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru was the Second one. ",
            "keyString": "854726s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event compel M.K Gandhi to withdraw the Nation's cooperation from the British Government?",
            "optionA": "  Jallianwala massacre ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagat singh Hanging ",
            "optionC": "  Lathi charge ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon cooperation movement was led by Mahatma Gandhi after the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre and lasted from 1920 to February 1922. It aimed to resist British rule in India through non-violent means, or \"Ahimsa\". The non-cooperation movement was launched on 1 August 1920 and withdrawn in February 1922 after the Chauri Chaura incident. ",
            "keyString": "854894s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement was withdrawn in 1922 because of",
            "optionA": "  Gandhi's ill health ",
            "optionB": "  The Congress' extremist policies ",
            "optionC": "  Afervent appeal by the government to do so ",
            "optionD": "  Violence erupting at Chauri Chaura ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi feared that the movement might lead to popular violence. The non-cooperation movement was launched on 1 August 1920 and withdrawn in February 1922 after the Chauri Chaura incident. ",
            "keyString": "905840s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hindu-Muslim unity had been particularly reflected in the __________ Movement",
            "optionA": "  Swadeshi ",
            "optionB": "  Quit India ",
            "optionC": "  Khilafat ",
            "optionD": "  Civil Disobedience ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Khilafat Movement saw the combined efforts of the Hindus and the Muslims under the supervision of the Indian National Congress against the British Raj. ",
            "keyString": "906067s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan, better known as Frontier Gandhi, organised the Red Shirt Movement in the NorthWest Frontier Province (NWFP) for",
            "optionA": "  countering the communal propaganda of the Muslim League  ",
            "optionB": "  establishing separate Pakhtoonistan ",
            "optionC": "  social and religious reforms ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Abdul Ghaffar Khan, better known as Frontier Gandhi, organised the Red Shirt Movement in the NorthWest Frontier Province (NWFP) for social and religious reforms. He was called the Frontier Gandhi. His followers were pledged to nonviolence, and they derived their popular title from the red colour of their shirts. Ghaffar Khan then advocated Pakhtunistan\u2014the concept of an independent Pashtun state, drawn from both the Pakistan and Afghan frontier districts. ",
            "keyString": "906257s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has been called the 'Heroine' of the 1942 Quit India Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Sucheta Kripalani ",
            "optionC": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionD": "  Aruna Asaf Ali ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAruna Asaf Ali (nee Aruna Ganguly; 16 July 1909 \u2013 29 July 1996) was an Indian independence activist. She is widely remembered for hoisting the Indian National flag at the Gowalia Tank maidan in Bombay during the Quit India Movement, 1942. ",
            "keyString": "906433s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why was the Khilafat Movement started?",
            "optionA": "  To protest against the injustice done to Egypt ",
            "optionB": "  To protest against the injustice done to Arabia ",
            "optionC": "  To protest against the injustice done to Persia ",
            "optionD": "  To protest against the injustice done to Turkey ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhilafat movement was started by Ali brothers-shaukat Ali and mohammad ali -in protest against the injustices done to Turkey after the first world war. Turkey was important to the Indian Muslims as the sultan of turkey was also the 'caliph' and was head of Muslims all over the world. ",
            "keyString": "906646s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Poorna Swaraj' (Complete Independence) was declared to be the goal of the Indian National Congress in its session of",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow, 1916 ",
            "optionB": "  Lahore, 1929 ",
            "optionC": "  Tripuri, 1939 ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore, 1940 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPoorna Swaraj was declared in the Lahore session 1929, Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru was the chairman of this session. ",
            "keyString": "959994s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first session of Indian National Congress was held in",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Lahore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHume organised the first meeting in Bombay with the approval of the Viceroy Lord Dufferin. Womesh Chandra Bonnerjee was the first president of Congress; the first session was attended by 72 delegates. ",
            "keyString": "960209s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first session of the Indian National Congress held?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first session of indian National Congress held at Bombay on 28 Dec 1885 under the Presidentship of WC Banarjee. ",
            "keyString": "960395s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress was founded in December 1885 at__________",
            "optionA": "  Bombay ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 28 December 1885, the Indian National Congress was founded at Gokuldas Tejpal Sanskrit College in Bombay, with 72 delegates in attendance. ",
            "keyString": "960574s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the President of Indian National congress when the Mountbatten Plan of independence was accepted?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionC": "  Maulana Azad ",
            "optionD": "  Acharya J. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Session of 1947 held at Meerut Acharya J.BKripalani was the President of Indian National Congress when Mountbatten plan of independence was accepted. ",
            "keyString": "960754s38m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Shuddhi Movement, involving the conversion of non-Hindus to Hinduism, was started by",
            "optionA": "  Swami Vivekanand ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Swami Dayanand Saraswati ",
            "optionD": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe socio-political movement, derived from ancient rite of shuddhikaran, or purification was started by the Arya Samaj, and its founder Swami Dayanand Saraswati and his followers like Swami Shraddhanand, who also worked on the Sangathan consolidation aspect of Hinduism, in North India, especially Punjab in early 1900s, though it gradually spread across India. Shuddhi had a social reform agenda behind its belligerent rationale and was aimed at abolishing the practise of untouchability by converting outcasts from other religions to Hinduism and integrating them into the mainstream community by elevating their position, and instilling self-confidence and self-determination in them. ",
            "keyString": "52230s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following historical events in the chronological order of their occurrence\nI. Non-Cooperation Movement\nII. Civil Disobedience Movement\nIII. Chauri - Chaura",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III ",
            "optionB": "  I, III, II ",
            "optionC": "  II, I, III ",
            "optionD": "  III, II, I ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following historical events in the chronological order of their occurrence are Non-Cooperation Movement- 1920, Chauri Chaura-1922, Civil Disobedience Movement- 1930. ",
            "keyString": "52441s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who, among the following, was the pioneer of social reform movements in 19th century India?",
            "optionA": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Devendra Nath Tegore ",
            "optionD": "  Keshav Chandra Sen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Ram Mohan Roy is considered as the pioneer of modern Indian Renaissance for the remarkable reforms he brought in the 18th and 19th century India. Among his efforts, the abolition of the brutal and inhuman Sati Pratha was the most prominent. ",
            "keyString": "52628s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1930, Mahatma Gandhi started the Civil Disobedience Movement from",
            "optionA": "  Wardha ",
            "optionB": "  Sevagram ",
            "optionC": "  Sabarmati ",
            "optionD": "  Dandi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi led the Dandi March from his base, Sabarmati Ashram, 240 miles (384 km) to the coastal village of Dandi, which was at a small town called Navsari (now in the state of Gujarat) to produce salt without paying the tax, growing numbers of Indians joined them along the way. ",
            "keyString": "52809s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the founder of the Boy Scouts and Civil Guides Movement in India?",
            "optionA": "  Richard Temple ",
            "optionB": "  Baden Powell ",
            "optionC": "  Charles Andrew ",
            "optionD": "  Robert Montgomery ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRobert Baden-Powell, the founder of the Scout movement. He was enamoured by the book and formed one of India's first Scout groups for native boys. ",
            "keyString": "52975s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi was first arrested, during 'Satyagrah' in the year",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1913 ",
            "optionD": "  1917 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 10 January 1908 Mahatma Gandhi was arrested for the first time in South Africa for refusing to carry an obligatory identity document card commonly known as the 'pass'. Gandhi was released in February after negotiations with the government. ",
            "keyString": "142743s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Mahatma Gandhi was arrested who among the following took over the leadership of Salt Satyagraha ?",
            "optionA": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Sardar Vallabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionC": "  Abbas Tayyabji ",
            "optionD": "  Maulana Abdul Kalarn Azad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi appointed Tyabji, at age seventy-six, to replace him as leader of the Salt Satyagraha in May 1930 after Gandhi's arrest. Tyabji was arrested soon afterward and imprisoned by the British Indian Government. Gandhi and others respectfully called Tyabji the \"Grand Old Man of Gujarat\". ",
            "keyString": "143039s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At midnight on December 31, 1929 who unfurled the tricolor flag on Indian Independence on the banks of the Ravi at Lahore?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Subhas Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe flag of India was hoisted by Jawaharlal Nehru on 31 December 1929 on the banks of Ravi river, in Lahore, modern-day Pakistan. The Congress asked the people of India to observe 26th of January as Independence Day. ",
            "keyString": "143288s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the first Independence day unofficially celebrated before Independence?",
            "optionA": "  On 26th January 1929 ",
            "optionB": "  On 26th January 1931 ",
            "optionC": "  On 26th January 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  On 26th January 1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCawnpore had celebrated first independence on Jan 26, 1930. It was 2 am in the morning when the citizens of Kanpur woke up with patriotism and enthusiasm, ready to carry out a peaceful procession to celebrate their first Independence Day in the British Regime. ",
            "keyString": "143521s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In what session did Congress declared complete Independence (Poorna Swaraj) as its goal?",
            "optionA": "  Lahore session held in 1929 ",
            "optionB": "  Madras session held in 1927 ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmadabad session held in 1921 ",
            "optionD": "  Gaya session held in 1922 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian National Congress held its annual session in December 1929. It voted for \u201cpurna swaraj\u201d or complete independence as against a dominion status for India and passed a resolution fixing the last Sunday of January 1930 \u2014 it was coincidentally January 26 \u2014 as Independence Day. Lahore session held in 1929. ",
            "keyString": "143742s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Champaran Satyagraha was related to",
            "optionA": "  Indigo ",
            "optionB": "  Mill-owners ",
            "optionC": "  Plague ",
            "optionD": "  Fresh assessment of land ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChamparan Satyagraha was related to indigo held in 1917. It was Gandhiji's first Satyagraha movement against \"Teen Kathiya System\". ",
            "keyString": "245210s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year salt Satyagraha took place?",
            "optionA": "  1929 ",
            "optionB": "  1930 ",
            "optionC": "  1931 ",
            "optionD": "  1932 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the year 1930 Salt satyagraha took place, it was also known as Dandi March initiated by Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "245544s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bardoli Satyagraha was led by",
            "optionA": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Morarji Desai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bardoli Satyagraha, 1928 was a movement in the independence struggle led by Sardar Vallabhai Patel for the farmers of Bardoli against the unjust raising of taxes.",
            "keyString": "245788s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following years 26th January was celebrated as an independence day?",
            "optionA": "  1930 ",
            "optionB": "  1929 ",
            "optionC": "  1942 ",
            "optionD": "  1946 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1930 when declaration of Indian Independence (Purna Swaraj) was proclaimed by the Indian National Congress opposed to the Dominion Status offered by British reign, 26th Jan 1930, was celebrated as an Independence day. ",
            "keyString": "246024s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When is the Independence Day of Pakistan celebrated?",
            "optionA": "  15th August, 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  4th July, 1947 ",
            "optionC": "  16th August, 1947 ",
            "optionD": "  14th August, 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the basis of Mountbatten plan it was declared that India will be divided into two dominion states i.e. India(15 Aug. 1947) and Pakistan (14 Aug. 1947). Pakistan gained independence on August 14,1947.",
            "keyString": "246246s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had pioneered the Khilafat Movement?",
            "optionA": "  The Ali brothers ",
            "optionB": "  MA Jinnah ",
            "optionC": "  Syed Ahmed Khan ",
            "optionD": "  RM Sayani ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA campaign in defense of the caliph was launched, led in India by the brothers Shaukat and Mu\u1e25ammad Ali and by Abul Kalam Azad. The leaders joined forces with Mahatma Gandhi's noncooperation movement for Indian freedom, promising nonviolence in return for his support of the Khilafat movement. ",
            "keyString": "315789s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement started in",
            "optionA": "  1870 ",
            "optionB": "  1920 ",
            "optionC": "  1921 ",
            "optionD": "  1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-Cooperation Movement was started on 1st August, 1920 under the leadership of Mahatma Gandhi. This movement was suspended by Mahatma Gandhi after Chauri Chaura Conspiracy on Feb 5, 1922. ",
            "keyString": "315988s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The objective(s) of the Kuka Movement in the Punjab was/were",
            "optionA": "  To purify Sikh religion of its abuses and superstitions ",
            "optionB": "  The revival of Sikh sovereignty ",
            "optionC": "  Both A and B above  ",
            "optionD": "  The revival of the Khalsa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Kuka was a religio-political movement in Punjab. Kukas were not part of the main-stream Sikhism of the Sikhs. They wanted caste-abolition, permission of intermarriages, widow-remarriages, abstinence from desi liquor, meat and drugs. ",
            "keyString": "316166s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the non-cooperation movement started by M.K Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  After Rowlatt Act ",
            "optionB": "  Chauri-Chaura incident ",
            "optionC": "  Jalliawala bagh Massacre ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was led by Mahatma Gandhi after the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre and lasted from 1920 to February 1922. It aimed to resist British rule in India through non-violent means, or \"Ahimsa\". The non-cooperation movement was launched on 1 August 1920 and withdrawn in February 1922 after the Chauri Chaura incident. ",
            "keyString": "316337s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the main cause for starting of the Quit India Movement in 1942 ?",
            "optionA": "  Severe unrest among the people ",
            "optionB": "  Report of Simon Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Failure of the Cripps Mission ",
            "optionD": "  British involved in the world was-II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCripps mission failed to fulfil the desires of Indian political leaders of different political parties to make Constitution assembly. So, INC committee and Gandhi ji decided to launch a movement on 8 Aug 1942 named Quit India Movement from Gwalia Tank Maidan(Mumbai).Gandhi ji gave the slogan \" Do or Die'. ",
            "keyString": "316498s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi launched the Civil Disobedience Movement on March 12, 1930 by",
            "optionA": "  asking the Viceroy through a letter containing Eleven Points Programme to remove the evils of the British rule ",
            "optionB": "  Dandi March to break the Salt Laws ",
            "optionC": "  asking the people to take Poorna Swaraj Pledge ",
            "optionD": "  launching the non-payment of taxes campaign ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 24-day march lasted from 12 March 1930 to 6 April 1930 as a direct action campaign of tax resistance and nonviolent protest against the British salt monopoly. It gained worldwide attention which gave impetus to the Indian independence movement and started the nationwide Civil Disobedience Movement. ",
            "keyString": "376262s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The non cooperation movement was called off due to",
            "optionA": "  Jallianwalla Bagh Tragedy ",
            "optionB": "  Chauri Chaura Incident ",
            "optionC": "  Poona pact ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhi-Irwin pact ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon-Cooperation movement started in 1920 under the leadership of M.K Gandhi. Non-Violence was basic and compulsory feature of this movement but in Chauri- Chaura (5th Feb, 1922) the principle of non-violence was not taken care of and Gandhi suspended the movement in Bardoli on 13 Feb, 1922. ",
            "keyString": "376815s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Socialism is essentially a movement of",
            "optionA": "  Intellectuals ",
            "optionB": "  The poor people ",
            "optionC": "  The middle classes ",
            "optionD": "  The workers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSocialism is a social and economic system characterized by social ownership of the means of production and co-operative management of the economy. Modern socialism originated from an 18th-century intellectual and working class political movement that criticised the effects of industrialization and private property on society. So it is essentially a movement of the workers. ",
            "keyString": "377196s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the another name of 'Quit India movement'?",
            "optionA": "  Khilafat Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Home Rule Movement ",
            "optionD": "  August Kranti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Quit India Movement, or the 'August Movement', was a movement launched at the Bombay session of the All-India Congress Committee by Mahatma Gandhi on 8 August 1942, during World War II, demanding an end to British Rule of India. ",
            "keyString": "377453s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the correct chronological order of the following events?\nI. Quit India Movement\nII. Shimla Conference\nIII. Poona Pact\nIV. Cabinet Mission",
            "optionA": "  II, IV, I, III ",
            "optionB": "  III, IV,II, I ",
            "optionC": "  III, I, II, IV ",
            "optionD": "  IV, II, III, I ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCorrect Chronological order is: Poona Pact (1932), Quit India movement(1942), Shimla conference (1945), Cabinet mission (1946). ",
            "keyString": "377789s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not included in Pakistan by the Independence Act?",
            "optionA": "  East Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  The West Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Sind ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWest Bengal was not included in Pakistan by the Independence Act. ",
            "keyString": "443944s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the August Kranti pulled back?",
            "optionA": "  1947 ",
            "optionB": "  1942 ",
            "optionC": "  1943 ",
            "optionD": "  1945 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn August 8, 1942 Mahatma Gandhi and the All-India Congress Committee (AICC) launched the Quit India Movement or Bharat Chodo Andolan at the Bombay session. As the Quit India Movement was launched in August, it is also known as August Movement or August Kranti. ",
            "keyString": "444164s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has written the book \"Tuzuk-i- jahangiri\"?",
            "optionA": "  Abul fazl ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Mulla daud ",
            "optionD": "  Abdul haq ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTuzuk-i-Jahangiri is the autobiographical account of the Mughal Emperor jahangir (1605-1627 AD). It is variously called Tarikh-i-Salimxahi, Tuzuk-i-Jahangiri, Karnama-i- Jahangiri, Waqiat-i-Jahangiri and Jahangirnamah etc. Jahangir himself wrote this book. ",
            "keyString": "444824s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced the Ryotwari System in India?",
            "optionA": "  Munro and Charles Reed ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  John shore ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRyotwari System was introduced by Thomas Munro in 1820. Major areas of introduction include Madras, Bombay, parts of Assam and Coorgh provinces of British India. In Ryotwari System the ownership rights were handed over to the peasants. British Government collected taxes directly from the peasants. ",
            "keyString": "449676s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Gandhiji, which of the following are the major means of Satyagraha ?\nI. non-cooperation\nII. Strike,\nIII. Demonstration\nIV. Civil disobedience",
            "optionA": "  I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  I and IV are correct ",
            "optionC": "  II and IV are correct ",
            "optionD": "  III and IV are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor means of Satyagraha of Gandhiji was Non-cooperation and civil disobedience. ",
            "keyString": "450147s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kuka movement started in mid-nineteenth century in",
            "optionA": "  Western Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Bharat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInitially started as a religious movement with a view to reforming the Sikh religion by purging it of the degenerate features, Kuka movement, founded in 1840 in Western Punjab, turned into a political struggle against the British. The founder of Kuka movement was Bhagat Jawahar Mal. ",
            "keyString": "535582s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The issue on which the Civil disobedience movement of 1930 was launched was",
            "optionA": "  Equal employment opportunities for Indians ",
            "optionB": "  The proposed execution of Bhagat Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Salt monopoly exercised by the British Government ",
            "optionD": "  Complete freedom ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn March 12, 1930, Indian independence leader Mohandas Gandhi begins a defiant march to the sea in protest of the British monopoly on salt, his boldest act of civil disobedience yet against British rule in India. The issue on which the Civil disobedience movement of 1930 was launched was Salt monopoly exercised by the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "535769s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The introduction of 'Western Education' and English language as medium of instruction led the foundation for the rise and growth of nationalism in India.\nReason (R): The Indian National Movement would not have been possible without the English language as the medium",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R is true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R is true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnglish was made the medium of instruction in India's schools in 1835, and many Indians increasingly started learning english. ",
            "keyString": "535930s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Khilafat Movement was launched to protest against the humiliation of",
            "optionA": "  The Turkish Caliph ",
            "optionB": "  Aga Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Ali Jinnah ",
            "optionD": "  Abdul Kalam Azad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The Khilafat Movement was launched to protest against the humiliation of the Turkish Caliph by allied powers after the end of first world war. ",
            "keyString": "536089s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following reform movements was the first to be started in the 19th Century?",
            "optionA": "  Prathana Samaj ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmo Samaj ",
            "optionC": "  Arya Samaj ",
            "optionD": "  Rama Krishna Mission ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrahmo Samaj was the first to be started in 19th century. It was established by Raja Ram Mohan Roy in 1828. Brahmo Samaj is the societal component of Brahmoism, which began as a monotheistic reformist movement of the Hindu religion that appeared during the Bengal Renaissance.",
            "keyString": "536245s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the main objective of the Wahabi movement which during 1852-70 was particularly active in the Punjab, Bengal, Bihar and the NWFP?",
            "optionA": "  To oust the British from India ",
            "optionB": "  To overthrow the Sikhs in the Punjab and the British in Bengal and to restore Muslim power in India ",
            "optionC": "  To eradicate religious corruption from Muslim society ",
            "optionD": "  To organise the Muslims into a nationalist community ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main objective of the Wahabi movement which during 1852-70 was particularly active in the Punjab, Bengal, Bihar and the NWFP was To overthrow the Sikhs in the Punjab and the British in Bengal and to restore Muslim power in India. ",
            "keyString": "720294s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Act of Indian Independence, the boundaries of East Bengal, West Bengal and Assam would be determined by",
            "optionA": "  The National Congress ",
            "optionB": "  The Muslim League ",
            "optionC": "  The Award of a Boundary Commission ",
            "optionD": "  The People living in those boundary areas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Act of Indian Independence, the boundaries of East Bengal, West Bengal and Assam would be determined by the Award of a Boundary Commission. ",
            "keyString": "721393s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The spark for the Swadeshi Movement was the __________ decision to partition Bengal",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  British ",
            "optionC": "  Dutch ",
            "optionD": "  Portuguese ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Curzon asked Queen Victoria to separate Bengal. Because they were scared if the Muslims and Hindus got together they could start a war. 500 meetings were held in East Bengal alone. The Swadeshi movement had genesis in the anti-partition movement which started to oppose the British decision to partition Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "722219s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following historical events in the chronological order of their occurrence.\nI. Champaran Satyagraha\nII. Partition of Bengal\nIII. Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III ",
            "optionB": "  II, III, I ",
            "optionC": "  II, I, III ",
            "optionD": "  I, III, II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following historical events in the chronological order of their occurrence are Partition of Bengal- 1905, Champaran Satyagrah - 1917 and Jallianwala Bagh -1919. ",
            "keyString": "723170s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The swadeshi movement in Bengal started on __________",
            "optionA": "  1902 ",
            "optionB": "  1905 ",
            "optionC": "  1908 ",
            "optionD": "  1909 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Swadeshi movement started with the partition of Bengal by the Viceroy of India, Lord Curzon in 1905 and continued up to 1911. It was the most successful of the pre-Gandhian movement. Its chief architects were Aurobindo Ghosh, Lokmanya Bal Gangadhar Tilak, Bipin Chandra Pal and Lala Lajpat Rai. ",
            "keyString": "723851s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following movement was NOT led by Mahatma Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Champarah Satyagraha ",
            "optionB": "  Wahabi Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Non-Coorperation Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Civil Disobedience Movenment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWahabi Movement was an Islamic movement centred around Patna, it tried to purify Islam by eliminating all the Unislamic practices. ",
            "keyString": "820866s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following movements was not led by Mahatma Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Quit India Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Swadeshi Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Non-Cooperation Movement ",
            "optionD": "  Civil Disobedience Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwadeshi Movement (1905) was not led by Mahatma Gandhi. This movement was related to Partition of Bengal by Lord Curzon. ",
            "keyString": "821470s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nirankari movement was started by__________",
            "optionA": "  Baba Dyal Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Ranjit Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Lal Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Tej Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nirankari movement was founded by Dayal Das (died 1855), who belonged to a half-Sikh, half-Hindu community in Peshawar. He believed that God is formless, or nirankar (hence the name Nirankari). ",
            "keyString": "822047s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ was prominent in the Labour and Socialist movements, a member of the Fabian Society and Social Democratic Federation, and took an active part in Trade Union work among unskilled labourers",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  H. P. Blavatsky ",
            "optionC": "  W. T. Stead ",
            "optionD": "  H. S. Olcott ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant (1847\u20131933), second President of The Theosophical Society from 1907 to 1933, was described as a \u2018Diamond Soul\u2019, for she had many brilliant facets to her character.She was an outstanding orator of her time, a champion of human freedom, educationist, philanthropist, and author with more than three hundred books and pamphlets to her credit. ",
            "keyString": "822574s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following place where the first meeting/session of the Indian National Congress was held?",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay ",
            "optionC": "  Madras ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first meeting was originally scheduled for Pune but due to plague outbreak, the venue was shifted to Mumbai. The first Session of INC was held from 28-31 December 1885, and was attended by 72 delegates. A O Hume assumed office as the General Secretary. Womesh Chandra Bonnerjee of Calcutta was elected President. ",
            "keyString": "823139s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the author of the Book, the Indian War of Independence, 1857?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Syed Ahmad Khan ",
            "optionB": "  V. ",
            "optionC": " Savarkar ",
            "optionD": "  R. S. Sharma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian War of Independence is an Indian nationalist history of the 1857 revolt by Vinayak Damodar Savarkar that was first published in 1909. ",
            "keyString": "892080s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the earliest and the best known mutinies before the Revolt of 1857 was",
            "optionA": "  the Native Infantry Mutiny (1824) ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Soldiers Mutiny at Vellore (1806) ",
            "optionC": "  Sholapur Mutiny (1838) ",
            "optionD": "  Assam Soldiers Mutiny (1824) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vellore Mutiny was one of the earliest sign of a great mutiny coming up in 1857. The Vellore Mutiny was a major act of defiance that took place on July 10, 1806 and marked the first ever large-scale and violent mutiny by Indian sepoys against the East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "892726s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following place, was not an important centre of the Revolt of 1857 ?",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionC": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionD": "  Lucknow ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgra was not the centre of the revolt on 1857. Other important cities of this revolt were Kanpur, Jhansi, Lucknow, Gwalior. ",
            "keyString": "893298s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. The rebels lacked effective leadership.\nII. They did not get the support of the civilian people anywhere in the country.\nIII. There was no central organisation to guide them.\nIV. Their military equipment was inferior to that of the English.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct related the causes for the failure of the Great Revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  I, III & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II & III ",
            "optionC": "  III & IV ",
            "optionD": "  II, III & IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe causes for the failure of the Great Revolt of 1857 were The rebels lacked effective leadership, There was no central organisation to guide them and Their military equipment was inferior to that of the English. ",
            "keyString": "893821s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who are among the following leaders of the Revolt of 1857 managed to escape to Nepal?\nI. Kunwar Singh\nII. Nana Saheb\nIII. Begum of Awadh\nIV. Bakht Khan",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II and IV ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNana Saheb and Begum of Awadh are among the following leaders of the Revolt of 1857 managed to escape to Nepal. ",
            "keyString": "894334s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following played an important role in Gadhar Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Shyamiji Krishna Verma ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionC": "  Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionD": "  Vishnu Ganesh Pingle ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLala Hardayal played an important role in Gadhar Movement, the head office of Gadhar Party was located in San Francisco. ",
            "keyString": "969971s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following events in correct sequence with reference to the Indian freedom struggle\nI. Passing of 'Indian Press Act'\nII. Surat Split of Congress\nIII. Launch of Non-Cooperation Movement IV. Passing of 'Rowlatt Act'",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III, IV ",
            "optionB": "  II, I, III, IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, I, IV, III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, IV, III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEvents in correct sequence with reference to the Indian freedom struggle are Surat Split of Congress- 1907, Passing of 'Indian Press Act'- 1910, Passing of 'Rowlatt Act'- 1919, Launch of Non-Cooperation Movement- 1920. ",
            "keyString": "971591s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________ joined the National Secular Society in 1874 and worked in the free thought and radical movements led by Charles Bradlaugh, MP",
            "optionA": "  Annie Besant ",
            "optionB": "  Tarachand Chakravarty ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " R. Mukhopadhyaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnie Besant joined the National Secular Society in 1874 and worked in the free thought and radical movements led by Charles Bradlaugh, MP. ",
            "keyString": "972759s39m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At the Calcutta session of the Indian National Congress (INC) held in 1906 the flag of Swaraj for India was unfurled by",
            "optionA": "  AO Hume ",
            "optionB": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionC": "  GK Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  BG Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the Calcutta session of the Indian National Congress (INC) held in 1906 the flag of Swaraj for India was unfurled by Dadabhai Naoroji. ",
            "keyString": "48820s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader gave the safety valve theory for Indian National Congress and said that it was brain child of Lord Dufferin?",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Nairoji ",
            "optionB": "  M N Roy ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSafety valve theory was given by Lala Lajpat Rai in 1916 in his book \u2018Young India\u2019. It describes INC as the safety valve for british indian empire. ",
            "keyString": "49841s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress and the Muslim League came to each other in 1916 at",
            "optionA": "  Lahore ",
            "optionB": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionC": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionD": "  Haripura ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLucknow Pact, (December 1916), agreement made by the Indian National Congress headed by Maratha leader Bal Gangadhar Tilak and the All-India Muslim League led by Muhammad Ali Jinnah; it was adopted by the Congress at its Lucknow session on December 29 and by the league on Dec. 31, 1916. ",
            "keyString": "50456s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Eradication of all possible race, creed or provincial prejudices among all lovers of India.\nII. Promotion of personal intimacy among all the earnest workers in the cause of India.\nIII. Formulation of popular demands.\nIV. Organisation of a violent struggle for the political emancipation of India.\nWhich of the above statement(s) is/are correct related to the aims of the Indian National Congress in the early phases?",
            "optionA": "  I, II & III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II & III ",
            "optionC": "  III & IV ",
            "optionD": "  II & III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe above statement(s) is/are correct related to the aims of the Indian National Congress in the early phases are Eradication of all possible race, creed or provincial prejudices among all lovers of India, Promotion of personal intimacy among all the earnest workers in the cause of India and Formulation of popular demands. ",
            "keyString": "51060s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress was formed __________",
            "optionA": "  1885 ",
            "optionB": "  1887 ",
            "optionC": "  1888 ",
            "optionD": "  1895 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 28 December 1885, the Indian National Congress was founded at Gokuldas Tejpal Sanskrit College in Bombay, with 72 delegates in attendance. Hume assumed office as the General Secretary, and Womesh Chunder Bonnerjee of Calcutta was elected President. ",
            "keyString": "51599s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Revolt of 1857 in Awadh and Lucknow was led by",
            "optionA": "  Wajid Ali Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Begum Hazrat Mahal ",
            "optionC": "  Asaf-ud-daula ",
            "optionD": "  Begum Zeenat Mahal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Indian Mutiny, from 1857 to 1858, Begum Hazrat Mahal's band of supporters, led by Raja Jailal Singh, rebelled against the forces of the British; later, they seized control of Lucknow and she declared her son, Birjis Qadra, as the ruler (Wali) of Oudh. ",
            "keyString": "125657s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Revolt of 1857 was a prolonged period of armed uprising as well as rebellions in Northern and Central India against British. It began in Meerut by Indian troops (sepoys) in the service of the British East India Company and later spread to Delhi, Agra, Awadh, Kanpur, Chambal and Lucknow.\n",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Awadh ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay ",
            "optionD": "  The Chambal Region ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 1857 revolt did not acquire much intensity in Bombay. ",
            "keyString": "126229s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements best explains the nature of revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  The last effort of the old political order to regain\npower ",
            "optionB": "  Mutiny of a section of sepoys of the British Army ",
            "optionC": "  A struggle of the common people to overthrow\ncommon rule ",
            "optionD": "  An effort to establish a limited Indian nation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe revolt of 1857 began under the leadership of Bahadur Shah Zafar and it was the last effort of old Political order to regain power. ",
            "keyString": "126721s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Mughal emperor occupying the throne of Delhi when the revolt of 1857 took place",
            "optionA": "  Shah Alam II ",
            "optionB": "  Jahandar Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBahadur Shah Zafar was a nominal Emperor, as the Mughal Empire existed in name only and his authority was limited only to the walled city of Old Delhi (Shahjahanbad). Following his involvement in the Indian Rebellion of 1857, the British exiled him to Rangoon in British-controlled Burma (now in Myanmar), after convicting him on conspiracy charges. ",
            "keyString": "127188s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following upheavals took place In Bengal immediately after the revolt of 1857?",
            "optionA": "  Santhal rebellion ",
            "optionB": "  Indigo disturbances ",
            "optionC": "  Sanyasi rebellion ",
            "optionD": "  Pabna disturbances ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indigo revolt (or Nil vidroha) was a peasant movement and subsequent uprising of indigo farmers against the indigo planters that arose in Bengal in 1859. ",
            "keyString": "127646s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Mahatma Gandhi arrested during the 'Quit India Movement' of 1942?",
            "optionA": "  7th August, 1942 ",
            "optionB": "  30th April, 1942 ",
            "optionC": "  9th August, 1942 ",
            "optionD": "  5th July, 1942 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 August 1942 at the All-India Congress Committee session in Bombay, Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi launched the 'Quit India' movement. The next day, Gandhi, Nehru and many other leaders of the Indian National Congress were arrested by the British Government. ",
            "keyString": "189795s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One time associated of Mahatma Ghandhi, broke off from him and launched a radical movement called 'self-respect movement'. Who was he?",
            "optionA": "  P. Thyagaraja Shetti ",
            "optionB": "  Chhatrapati Maharaj ",
            "optionC": "  E.V.Ramaswamy Naicker ",
            "optionD": "  Jyotirao Govindrao Phule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1925, Periyar E.V.Ramaswamy founded the Self-respect Movement. It was aimed at achieving a society where backward castes to have equal human rights. ",
            "keyString": "190422s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological order of the establishment of parties during Indian Struggle Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Indian National Congress, Justice Party, Swaraj party, Muslim League ",
            "optionB": "  Indian National Congress, Muslim League,  Justice Party, Swaraj party ",
            "optionC": "  Swaraj Party, Indian National Congress, Muslim League, Justice Party ",
            "optionD": "  Swaraj Party, Indian National Congress, Justice Party, Muslim League ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct chronological order of the establishment of parties during Indian Struggle Movement are Indian National Congress- 1885, Muslim League- 1906, Justice Party- 1917, Swaraj Party- 1923. ",
            "keyString": "192063s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The slogan of 'Vande Matram' was first adopted during the __________ Movement?",
            "optionA": "  Non-cooperation ",
            "optionB": "  Civil Disobedience ",
            "optionC": "  Swadeshi ",
            "optionD": "  Quit India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe slogan of Vande Matram was first adopted during Swadeshi Movement that was a part of the Indian Independence Movement. This movement is also referred to as Anti-Bengal Partition Movement. It took place between 1905 and 1911 when Lord Curzon partitioned the Bengal province into two. ",
            "keyString": "192651s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The earliest nationalist to commit political dacoities (a feature of the later revolutionary movements) was",
            "optionA": "  Jyotiba Phule ",
            "optionB": "  Chapekar brothers ",
            "optionC": "  Vasudev Balwant Phadke ",
            "optionD": "  Yatindra Das ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe earliest nationalist to commit political dacoities (a feature of the later revolutionary movements) was Vasudev Balwant Phadke. Vasudev Balwant Phadke was an Indian independence activist and revolutionary who sought India's independence from British. Phadke was moved by the plight of the farmer community during British Raj. Phadke believed that Swaraj was the only remedy for their ills. ",
            "keyString": "193205s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi gave the call to reject all foreign goods during the __________ Movement",
            "optionA": "  Khilafat ",
            "optionB": "  Non-cooperation ",
            "optionC": "  Swadeshi ",
            "optionD": "  Civil Disobedience ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Swadeshi movement, part of the Indian independence movement and the developing Indian nationalism, was an economic strategy aimed at removing the British Empire from power and improving economic conditions in India by following the principles of swadeshi which had some success. Strategies of the Swadeshi movement involved boycotting British products and the revival of domestic products and production processes. L. M. Bhole identifies five phases of the Swadeshi movement. Gandhi gave the call to reject all foreign goods during the Swadeshi Movement. ",
            "keyString": "264528s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gandhi had given out the stirring call of 'Do or Die' during the __________ Movement",
            "optionA": "  Non-cooperation ",
            "optionB": "  Khilafat ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Disobedience ",
            "optionD": "  Quit India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cripps Mission had failed, and on 8 August 1942, Gandhi made a call to Do or Die in his Quit India speech delivered in Bombay at the Gowalia Tank Maidan. ",
            "keyString": "265139s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vivian Derozio had been associated with the __________ movement",
            "optionA": "  Swadeshi ",
            "optionB": "  Back to the Vedas ",
            "optionC": "  Young Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Young India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Young Bengal was a group of radical Bengali free thinkers emerging from Hindu College, Calcutta. They were also known as Derozians, after their firebrand teacher at Hindu College, Henry Louis Vivian Derozio. ",
            "keyString": "265697s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year Lala Lajpat Rai was deported to Mandalay for organising the agrarian movement in Punjab?",
            "optionA": "  1905 ",
            "optionB": "  1907 ",
            "optionC": "  1909 ",
            "optionD": "  1911 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 1907 Punjab unrests were a period of unrest in the British Indian province of Punjab, principally around the Colonisation bill that was implemented in the province in 1906. This timeline has often been called the beginning of the freedom movement in Punjab. Important leaders of this movement include Lala Lajpat Rai, Het Thakkar, among others. In 1907, Lala Lajpat Rai was deported. ",
            "keyString": "266205s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was in command of the nationalist movement before Gandhi had assumed leadership of the Congress?",
            "optionA": "  C R Das ",
            "optionB": "  Motilal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Lala Lajpat Rai ",
            "optionD": "  Lokmanya Tilak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBal Gangadhar Tilak born as Keshav Gangadhar Tilak, was an Indian nationalist, teacher, lawyer and an independence activist. He was the first leader of the Indian Independence Movement. Lokmanya Tilak was in command of the nationalist movement before Gandhi had assumed leadership of the Congress. ",
            "keyString": "266702s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following events in a correct sequence of Indian National Movement\nI. Foundation of Indian National Congress\nII. Simon Commission\nIII. Home Rule Movement\nIV. Cabinet Mission",
            "optionA": "  I, III, II, IV ",
            "optionB": "  III, I, IV, II ",
            "optionC": "  I, II, IV, III ",
            "optionD": "  I, IV, III, II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following events in a correct sequence of Indian National Movement are Foundation of Indian National Congress- 1885, Home Rule Movement- 1916, Simon Commission- 1928 and Cabinet Mission- 1946. ",
            "keyString": "352303s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Non-Cooperation Movement got momentum under the leadership of Mahatma Gandhi and the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  1920-1922 ",
            "optionB": "  1922-1924 ",
            "optionC": "  1987-1989 ",
            "optionD": "  1990-1992 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-Cooperation Movement was pitched in under leadership of Mahatma Gandhi and the Indian National Congress from September 1920 to February 1922, marking a new awakening in the Indian Independence Movement. ",
            "keyString": "352926s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Eminent Tamil Poet C Subramania Bharati was associated with which of the following movements of the Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Extremist ",
            "optionB": "  Non-Cooperation ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Disobedience ",
            "optionD": "  Quit India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChinnaswami Subramania Bharati, also known as Bharathiyar, was a Tamil writer, poet, journalist, Indian independence activist and a social reformer from Tamil Nadu. Popularly known as \"Mahakavi Bharati\", he was a pioneer of modern Tamil poetry and is considered one of the greatest Tamil literary figures of all time. He belonged to the extremist wing of the Congress part. ",
            "keyString": "353473s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the freedom struggle a parallel movement launched in the Indian states (in the states ruled by the Indian rulers such as Kashmir, Nizam's Hyderabad, Travancore, etc.) was/were",
            "optionA": "  State People's Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Praja Mandal Movement ",
            "optionC": "  Both A and B above ",
            "optionD": "  Swaraj Movement ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe All India States Peoples' Conference (AISPC) was a conglomeration of political movements in the princely states of the British Raj, which were variously called Praja Mandals or Lok Parishads. The Praja Mandal movement was a part of the Indian independence movement from the 1920s in which people living in the princely states, who were subject to the rule of local aristocrats rather than the British Raj, campaigned against those feudatory rulers, and sometimes also the British administration, in attempts to improve their civil rights. ",
            "keyString": "353978s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khilafat Movement was organised by",
            "optionA": "  Jinnah ",
            "optionB": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Ali Brothers ",
            "optionD": "  Agha Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Khilafat movement, also known as the Indian Muslim movement (1919\u201324), was a pan-Islamist political protest campaign launched by Muslims of British India led by Shaukat Ali, Mohammad Ali Jauhar and Abul Kalam Azad to restore the caliph of the Ottoman Caliphate, who was considered the leader of Sunni Muslims, as an effective political authority. ",
            "keyString": "354468s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All India State's Peoples Conference formed in 1927 launched popular movements in",
            "optionA": "  Princely States ",
            "optionB": "  British Provinces ",
            "optionC": "  Hill Regions ",
            "optionD": "  Tribal Areas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first session of an All India States' People's Conference was held in Bombay in December 1927. The Conference brought together representatives from hundreds of Indian princely states, including Baroda, Bhopal, Travancore and Hyderabad. ",
            "keyString": "430517s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following freedom fighter opposes the Annie Besant's idea of launching Home Rule Movement?",
            "optionA": "  G. K. Gokhale ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tG. K. Gokhale freedom fighter opposes the Annie Besant's idea of launching Home Rule Movement. ",
            "keyString": "431137s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following trio leaders referred to as Lal, Bal and Pal during the freedom movement?",
            "optionA": "  Lala Lajpat Rai, Bal Gangadhar Tilak and Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionB": "  Lal Bahadur Shastri, Bal Gangadhar Tilak and Bipin Chandra Pal ",
            "optionC": "  Lal Bahadur Shastri, Bal Gangadhar Tilak and Gopala Krishna Gokhale ",
            "optionD": "  Lala Lajpat Rai, Bal Gangadhar Tilak and ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe three dynamic leaders of Lokmanya Tilak, Lala Lajpat Rai and Bipin Chandra Pal, who had been promoting self-reliance and opposing the monopoly of the British goods in India, famously came together as the Lal-Bal-Pal trio. ",
            "keyString": "431724s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, the Wahabi movement was started by __________",
            "optionA": "  1901 ",
            "optionB": "  1906 ",
            "optionC": "  1915 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough Shah Waliullah started it, the actual founder of the Wahabi movement in India was Syed Ahmed (1786-1831) of Raibareilly in Uttar Pradesh. He came in touch with Aziz and 1820-21 onwards started preaching the ideals of Islamic reforms. Syed Ahmed was the founder of wahabi movement in india. ",
            "keyString": "432246s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct related to the Non-cooperation Movement?\nI. It aimed to resist British rule in India through non violent means. Protestors would refuse to buy British goods, adopt the use of local handicrafts and picket liquor shops. \nII. The ideas of Ahimsa and nonviolence, and Gandhi's ability to rally hundreds of thousands of common citizens towards the cause of Indian independence, were first seen on a large scale in this movement through the summer 1920, they feared that the movement might lead to popular violence",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I & II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth statement(s) are correct related to the Non-cooperation Movement. It aimed to resist British rule in India through nonviolent means. Protestors would refuse to buy British goods, adopt the use of local handicrafts and picket liquor shops. The ideas of Ahimsa and nonviolence, and Gandhi's ability to rally hundreds of thousands of common citizens towards the cause of Indian independence, were first seen on a large scale in this movement through the summer 1920, they feared that the movement might lead to popular violence. ",
            "keyString": "432751s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year did the Indian National Congress split between moderates and extremists?",
            "optionA": "  1907 ",
            "optionB": "  1908 ",
            "optionC": "  1909 ",
            "optionD": "  1910 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In Surat Session of INC clearly divided into Garm Dal and Naram Dal. The Chairman was Ras Bihari Ghosh. It is also known as Surat-Split. ",
            "keyString": "525021s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ghadar Party was founded (November 1913) at San Francisco USA by",
            "optionA": "  Madam Bhikaji Cama ",
            "optionB": "  Lala Hardayal ",
            "optionC": "  Shyamji Krishana Verma ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1913, Pacific Coast Hindustan Association was founded by Lala Hardayal with Sohan Singh Bhakna as its president, which was called Ghadar Party. The members of this party were the immigrant sikhs of US and Canada. The first issue of The Ghadar, was published from San Francisco on November 1, 1913. ",
            "keyString": "636943s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair leader associated with the Revolt of 1857 is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Hazrat Mahal : Kanpur ",
            "optionB": "  Khan Bahadur Khan : Bareilly ",
            "optionC": "  Kunwar Singh : Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Bakht Khan : Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBegum Hazrat Mahal, also called as Begum of Awadh, was the second wife of Nawab Wajid Ali Shah. Wajid Ali Shah met her in his palace. She rebelled against the British East India Company during the Indian Rebellion of 1857. She finally found asylum in Nepal where she died in 1879. ",
            "keyString": "637301s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The administrative consequence of the Revolt of 1857 was transferred to power from",
            "optionA": "  East India Company to the British Crown ",
            "optionB": "  British Crown to the East India Company ",
            "optionC": "  East India Company to the Governor General ",
            "optionD": "  British Crown to the Board of Directors ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn August 2, 1858, less than a month after Canning proclaimed the victory of British arms, Parliament passed the Government of India Act, transferring British power over India from the East India Company, whose ineptitude was primarily blamed for the mutiny, to the crown. ",
            "keyString": "637576s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the initial success of the Revolt of 1857, the objective for which the leaders of the revolt worked was",
            "optionA": "  to restore the former glory to the Mughal empire ",
            "optionB": "  to form a Federation of Indian States under the aegis of Bhadur Shah II ",
            "optionC": "  elimination of foreign rule and return of the old order ",
            "optionD": "  each leader wanted to establish his own power in his respective region ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter the initial success of the Revolt of 1857, the objective for which the leaders of the revolt worked was elimination of foreign rule and return of the old order. ",
            "keyString": "638103s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Govind Dhondu Pant, popularly known was Nanasaheb, and one of the principal leaders of the Revolt of 1857, was the adopted heir and successor of",
            "optionA": "  Peshwa Baji Rao II ",
            "optionB": "  King of Jhansi ",
            "optionC": "  Madhav Rao Sindhia ",
            "optionD": "  Malhar Rao Holkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovind Dhondu Pant, popularly known was Nanasaheb, and one of the principal leaders of the Revolt of 1857, was the adopted heir and successor of Peshwa Baji Rao II. ",
            "keyString": "638455s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the absence of Gandhi, the Quit India Movement had been led by",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionC": "  Aruna Asaf Ali ",
            "optionD": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAruna Asaf Ali (n\u00e9e Aruna Ganguly; 16 July 1909 \u2013 29 July 1996) was an Indian independence activist. She is widely remembered for hoisting the Indian National flag at the Gowalia Tank maidan in Bombay during the Quit India Movement, 1942. ",
            "keyString": "732424s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two great socio-religious reformers of the 19th century who provided inspiration to the Indian National Movement were",
            "optionA": "  Dayanand Saraswati and Vivekananda ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Ram Mohan Roy and Debendra Nath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  MG Ranade and DK Karve ",
            "optionD": "  Keshab Chandra Sen and Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo great socio-religious reformers of the 19th century who provided inspiration to the Indian National Movement were Dayanand Saraswati and Vivekananda. ",
            "keyString": "733459s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement was suspended in February 1922 on account of",
            "optionA": "  the Chauri Chaura incident ",
            "optionB": "  Hindu Muslim riots ",
            "optionC": "  arrest of Mahatma Gandhi and his imprisonment for six years ",
            "optionD": "  all the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-cooperation movement was withdrawn because of the Chauri Chaura incident. Although he had stopped the national revolt single-handedly, on 10 March 1922, Gandhi was arrested. On 18 March 1922, he was imprisoned for six years for publishing seditious materials. ",
            "keyString": "734008s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bhoodan Movement had been started by",
            "optionA": "  M K Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya Kripalani ",
            "optionC": "  Jayaprakash Narayan ",
            "optionD": "  Vinoba Bhave ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhoodan Movement or Land Gift Movement, was a voluntary land reform movement in India, started by Acharya Vinoba Bhave in 1951 at Pochampally village which is now in Telangana, India and known as Bhoodan Pochampally. ",
            "keyString": "734491s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event was the reason for the withdrawn of non cooperation movement?",
            "optionA": "  Chauri Chaura incident ",
            "optionB": "  Jallianwala massacre ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhi Imprisionment ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Non-cooperation movement was withdrawn because of the Chauri Chaura incident. Although he had stopped the national revolt single-handedly, on 10 March 1922, Gandhi was arrested. This led to suppression of the movement and was followed by the arrest of other leaders. ",
            "keyString": "734739s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In December 1885, when the Indian National Congress was founded, AO Hume acted as its",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Vice-President ",
            "optionC": "  General Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Member of the Working Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 28 December 1885, the Indian National Congress was founded at Gokuldas Tejpal Sanskrit College in Bombay, with 72 delegates in attendance. Hume assumed office as the General Secretary, and Womesh Chunder Bonnerjee of Calcutta was elected President. ",
            "keyString": "797371s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following leader was not present in the very first meeting of Indian National Congress?",
            "optionA": "  Dadabhai Naoroji ",
            "optionB": "  Kashinath Trimbak Telang ",
            "optionC": "  Pherozeshah Mehta ",
            "optionD": "  Surendranath Banerjee ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first session of the National Conference, held in Calcutta on December 28 - 30, 1883, was attended by more than a hundred delegates from different parts of India. Surendranath Banerjee was not present in the very first meeting of Indian National Congress. ",
            "keyString": "797603s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress had been formed with the knowledge and approval of Lord",
            "optionA": "  Dufferin ",
            "optionB": "  Mountbatten ",
            "optionC": "  Ripon ",
            "optionD": "  Curzon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst meeting of the Congress was held in Bombay, with the approval of Lord Dufferin, the then-Viceroy. ",
            "keyString": "798014s40m7h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}